<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Giulio Fidente (aka Giulivo Navigante)</title><link href="http://giuliofidente.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://giuliofidente.com/feeds/category/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://giuliofidente.com/</id><updated>2013-05-14T16:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>ToDoist TIPS</title><link href="http://giuliofidente.com/2013/05/todoist-tips.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-05-14T16:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:giuliofidente.com,2013-05-14:2013/05/todoist-tips.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I was on the look out for some web (and portable) todo management application. I tried many as many are free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point I was forced to re-evaluate and re-define my own needs, there are indeed at least two different kinds of tracking applications. Some are like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://idonethis.com"&gt;iDoneThis&lt;/a&gt;, some sort of reporting tool, others are more like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dontforgetthemilk.com"&gt;Don't Forget The Milk&lt;/a&gt;, a pure todo managing application. What I needed was more something from the second group and my preference went to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://todoist.com"&gt;ToDoist&lt;/a&gt;, it's got the features I want, especially the time-setting thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of days after my sign up, they sent me an (automated) email listing a few &amp;quot;tips&amp;quot;. Well, I was going to consider that email as spam but after a quick read I realized the &amp;quot;tips&amp;quot; really were well picked up and had a much broader scope. I was somewhat already familiar with the principles but the list reinforced the concepts. I thought it was worth sharing, see for yourself, some extracts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Many of the emails you receive contain action items, but without a way to set due dates, priorities, and reminders, those emails often get forgotten.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same can be said for the other action items you put in the list!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
If possible don’t try to do several things at once. Use your to-do list to keep you focused and on track. By working systematically to complete each task on your list, you’ll get more done.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read that as a suggestion to prioritize the list and work on the one (or a few) item from the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Break big tasks into a number of smaller sub-tasks that can be completed in 1 hour or less.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn't enforce the 1 hour timeline, but the concept of splitting the bigger tasks into a number of smaller and &lt;em&gt;easier to track&lt;/em&gt; items remains valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
If your tasks aren’t accessible at all times, you’ll start to forget about them and miss opportunities to get things done.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to have separate lists for different purposes. Read, I don't mix work items with personal tasks, but I make sure my work todo list is easy to reach from any of the devices I use when working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
To improve your productivity, you need to be able to see how productive you are now and how your productivity levels change over time. Once you can see how your productive you are, you can work on figuring out which productivity tactics are working for you and improve your output.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="todo"></category><category term="todoist"></category></entry><entry><title>One more for Aaron</title><link href="http://giuliofidente.com/2013/01/one-more-for-aaron.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:giuliofidente.com,2013-01-13:2013/01/one-more-for-aaron.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yes, Aaron was the co-founder of Reddit and Avaaz. Aaron edited and contributed to the RSS specifications when he was 14. But that isn't the best part. Even for people like me, who only met Aaron on the internet, he was a lot more. From &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rememberaaronsw.tumblr.com/post/40372208044/official-statement-from-the-family-and-partner-of-aaron"&gt;Remember Aaron&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Aaron's commitment to social justice was profound, and defined his life. He was instrumental to the defeat of an Internet censorship bill; he fought for a more democratic, open, and accountable political system; and he helped to create, build, and preserve a dizzying range of scholarly projects that extended the scope and accessibility of human knowledge.
He used his prodigious skills as a programmer and technologist not to enrich himself but to make the Internet and the world a fairer, better place. His deeply humane writing touched minds and hearts across generations and continents.
He earned the friendship of thousands and the respect and support of millions more. Aaron's death is not simply a personal tragedy. It is the product of a criminal justice system rife with intimidation and prosecutorial overreach.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's worth repeat those words again: &lt;em&gt;used his prodigious skills as a programmer and technologist not to enrich himself but to make the Internet and the world a fairer, better place.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lessig.tumblr.com/post/40347463044/prosecutor-as-bully"&gt;Lawrence Lessig has called&lt;/a&gt; for this tragedy to be a basis for reform of computer crime laws, and the overzealous prosecutors who use them. You can read more about Aaron and the case also in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/farewell-aaron-swartz"&gt;EFF's farewell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="aaron swartz"></category></entry><entry><title>Long Life to Red Hat</title><link href="http://giuliofidente.com/2012/09/long-life-to-red-hat.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:giuliofidente.com,2012-09-29:2012/09/long-life-to-red-hat.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a job is just a way to earn some money. Rarely it is also fun. Sometimes it is fun instead but not suiting very well your principles and culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I'm a very lucky guy as I've got them all. And no it is not of Google that I'm talking about, this is &lt;strong&gt;better!&lt;/strong&gt;. It's &lt;strong&gt;better&lt;/strong&gt; because I've got many of the same benefits, including a thriving tech culture and a nice kitchen with free food and I've also got to work on open source and free software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free software! I mean free as in speech not as in beer. Software which can be reused, changed, improved, shared with and by other people and is not intended to hurt your privacy. To me that looks great, it is the living vision of the same people who brought to you (many years ago) the best-in-class OS, which also Google runs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, long life to Red Hat!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="red hat"></category></entry><entry><title>Napoli (Silicon Dust)</title><link href="http://giuliofidente.com/2012/04/napoli-silicon-dust.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:giuliofidente.com,2012-04-08:2012/04/napoli-silicon-dust.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/LemIPWHMbxc?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</summary><category term="silicon dust"></category><category term="napoli"></category></entry><entry><title>From beef to vegetables</title><link href="http://giuliofidente.com/2011/06/from-beef-to-vegetables.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-06-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:giuliofidente.com,2011-06-20:2011/06/from-beef-to-vegetables.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shifting from beef to vegetables for even a single day a week would in fact be more helpful in reducing greenhouse gases than shifting the entirety of one's diet to exclusively locally produced sources. See &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.criticalanimalstudies.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/2-JCAS-Vol-VIII-Issue-I-and-II-2010-Essay-GREEN-EGGS-AND-HAM-pp-8-32.doc"&gt;GREEN-EGGS-AND-HAM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="vegetables"></category><category term="beef"></category><category term="vegetarianism"></category></entry><entry><title>Learned helplessness</title><link href="http://giuliofidente.com/2009/02/learned-helplessness.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-02-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:giuliofidente.com,2009-02-16:2009/02/learned-helplessness.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learned helplessness is a psychological condition in which a human being or an animal has learned to act or behave helpless in a particular situation, even when it has the power to change its unpleasant or even harmful circumstance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learned helplessness theory is the view that clinical depression and related mental illnesses result from a perceived absence of control over the outcome of a situation (Seligman, 1975).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting? Continue on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learned_helplessness"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="learned helplessness"></category></entry></feed>