<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Giulio Fidente (aka Giulivo Navigante)</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.im/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.im/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.giuliofidente.im/</id><updated>2013-03-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Tumultuos</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.im/2013/03/tumultuos.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:www.giuliofidente.im,2013-03-10:2013/03/tumultuos.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A tumultuous post, written on a rush and with many external references... but worth sharing I thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While working to port (or reinit) this blog over to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, we in Italy had the elections. Not a word that I know describes how disgusted I am to learn that I share this country with a 25% circa of people who still voted for Berlusconi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least I found a good documentary (one more?) on this &amp;quot;Italian times&amp;quot; and it is called &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://girlfriendinacoma.eu/"&gt;Girlfriend in a Coma&lt;/a&gt;. Most of it is discussed by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Emmott"&gt;Bill Emmott&lt;/a&gt; and that is indeed what makes it so interesting. I share his view on the actual result coming from the elections. I suggest you to read his article on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/this-weeks-big-questions-are-the-italian-election-results-disastrous-or-hopeful-8517186.html"&gt;the Independent&lt;/a&gt; also to get a meaningful wrap up on the status quo, it includes comments for both Bersani and Grillo indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I'm not finished yet with the changes, I'm also getting my hands dirty on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://openstack.org/"&gt;OpenStack&lt;/a&gt; (starting with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/cinder/Cinder"&gt;Cinder&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/cinder/Tempest"&gt;Tempest&lt;/a&gt;)! Things at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.redhat.com/openstack/"&gt;RHOS&lt;/a&gt; are going well and it is good fun to work on this stuff, plus the block volumes management in the cloud really is area of big challenges. To my joyness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk to you soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="openstack"></category><category term="grillo"></category><category term="berlusconi"></category><category term="rhos"></category><category term="bill emmott"></category><category term="bersani"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="girlfriend in a coma"></category></entry><entry><title>One more for Aaron</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.im/2013/01/one-more-for-aaron.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:www.giuliofidente.im,2013-01-13:2013/01/one-more-for-aaron.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yes, Aaron was the co-founder of Reddit and Avaaz. Aaron edited and contributed to the RSS specifications when he was 14. But that isn't the best part. Even for people like me, who only met Aaron on the internet, he was a lot more. From &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rememberaaronsw.tumblr.com/post/40372208044/official-statement-from-the-family-and-partner-of-aaron"&gt;Remember Aaron&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Aaron's commitment to social justice was profound, and defined his life. He was instrumental to the defeat of an Internet censorship bill; he fought for a more democratic, open, and accountable political system; and he helped to create, build, and preserve a dizzying range of scholarly projects that extended the scope and accessibility of human knowledge.
He used his prodigious skills as a programmer and technologist not to enrich himself but to make the Internet and the world a fairer, better place. His deeply humane writing touched minds and hearts across generations and continents.
He earned the friendship of thousands and the respect and support of millions more. Aaron's death is not simply a personal tragedy. It is the product of a criminal justice system rife with intimidation and prosecutorial overreach.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's worth repeat those words again: &lt;em&gt;used his prodigious skills as a programmer and technologist not to enrich himself but to make the Internet and the world a fairer, better place.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lessig.tumblr.com/post/40347463044/prosecutor-as-bully"&gt;Lawrence Lessig has called&lt;/a&gt; for this tragedy to be a basis for reform of computer crime laws, and the overzealous prosecutors who use them. You can read more about Aaron and the case also in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/01/farewell-aaron-swartz"&gt;EFF's farewell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="aaron swartz"></category></entry><entry><title>Long Life to Red Hat</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.im/2012/09/long-life-to-red-hat.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:www.giuliofidente.im,2012-09-29:2012/09/long-life-to-red-hat.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a job is just a way to earn some money. Rarely it is also fun. Sometimes it is fun instead but not suiting very well your principles and culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I'm a very lucky guy as I've got them all. And no it is not of Google that I'm talking about, this is &lt;strong&gt;better!&lt;/strong&gt;. It's &lt;strong&gt;better&lt;/strong&gt; because I've got many of the same benefits, including a thriving tech culture and a nice kitchen with free food and I've also got to work on open source and free software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free software! I mean free as in speech not as in beer. Software which can be reused, changed, improved, shared with and by other people and is not intended to hurt your privacy. To me that looks great, it is the living vision of the same people who brought to you (many years ago) the best-in-class OS, which also Google runs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, long life to Red Hat!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="red hat"></category></entry><entry><title>Napoli (Silicon Dust)</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.im/2012/04/napoli-silicon-dust.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:www.giuliofidente.im,2012-04-08:2012/04/napoli-silicon-dust.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/LemIPWHMbxc?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</summary><category term="silicon dust"></category><category term="napoli"></category></entry><entry><title>From beef to vegetables</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.im/2011/06/from-beef-to-vegetables.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-06-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:www.giuliofidente.im,2011-06-20:2011/06/from-beef-to-vegetables.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shifting from beef to vegetables for even a single day a week would in fact be more helpful in reducing greenhouse gases than shifting the entirety of one's diet to exclusively locally produced sources. See &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.criticalanimalstudies.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/2-JCAS-Vol-VIII-Issue-I-and-II-2010-Essay-GREEN-EGGS-AND-HAM-pp-8-32.doc"&gt;GREEN-EGGS-AND-HAM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="vegetables"></category><category term="beef"></category><category term="vegetarianism"></category></entry><entry><title>Learned helplessness</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.im/2009/02/learned-helplessness.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-02-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:www.giuliofidente.im,2009-02-16:2009/02/learned-helplessness.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learned helplessness is a psychological condition in which a human being or an animal has learned to act or behave helpless in a particular situation, even when it has the power to change its unpleasant or even harmful circumstance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learned helplessness theory is the view that clinical depression and related mental illnesses result from a perceived absence of control over the outcome of a situation (Seligman, 1975).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting? Continue on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learned_helplessness"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="learned helplessness"></category></entry></feed>