<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Giulio Fidente (aka Giulivo Navigante)</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.com/feeds/tag/leopard-network-install.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.giuliofidente.com/</id><updated>2009-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>OS X Network Install using Linux (updates)</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.com/2009/01/os-x-network-install-using-linux-updates.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:www.giuliofidente.com,2009-01-06:2009/01/os-x-network-install-using-linux-updates.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you still remember &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.giuliofidente.com/2006/11/os-x-network-install-using-linux.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;? It was a good post about the OS X install via the network using a GNU/Linux install server. I went back to read and use it after a few days to install the version 10.5 (leopard) of OS X and it worked well but there's a couple of things missing in that post which I'd like to share here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems were mainly in mounting the leopard disc. If you try to do that on a GNU/Linux system you should only see some files about bootcamp, it is indeed a double format dvd which includes two sections, one is iso9660 formatted and another is hfs+ formatted. To find the files I mentioned, you'll have to mount the hfs+ formatted section ... which is hidden but you can find it using this very helpful link: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.64lines.com/mounting-hfs-plus"&gt;Mounting HFS+ Hybrid Disks on Linux&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, because of the additional steps, when you're at this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
dd if=/dev/hdc of=/tftpboot/macosx.img
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you'll have to replace /dev/hdc with the /dev/loop0 device created by the instructions linked before.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="osx network install"></category><category term="linux network install"></category><category term="leopard network install"></category><category term="fedoraplanet"></category></entry><entry><title>OS X Network Install using Linux</title><link href="http://www.giuliofidente.com/2006/11/os-x-network-install-using-linux.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2006-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Giulio Fidente</name></author><id>tag:www.giuliofidente.com,2006-11-01:2006/11/os-x-network-install-using-linux.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The title says it all. We're going to install an OS X client via network using a GNU/Linux box as DHCP/TFTP/NFS server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you'll want to setup your DHCP, TFTP and NFS server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default location for the TFTP server root on my system was &lt;code&gt;/tftpboot&lt;/code&gt;. It may be different on other distro so change at will. This directory is where we're going to put all the important files. Three files come from the OS X disc (although you'll have to rename two of them) and the fourth is a simple image of the OS X disc itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mount the Mac OS X disc and copy and rename the following files into your TFTP server root&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
cp /cdrom/System/Library/CoreServices/BootX /tftpboot/BootX
cp /cdrom/mach\_kernel /tftpboot/mach.macosx
cp /cdrom/System/Library/Extensions.mkext /tftpboot/mach.macosx.mkext
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unmount and make an image of the install disc in the TFTP server root&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
dd if=/dev/hdc of=/tftpboot/macosx.img
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On your NFS server, you'll want to modify &lt;code&gt;/etc/exports&lt;/code&gt; to include something like the following&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
/tftpboot/ mac-ip-address(ro,insecure)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where mac-ip-address is the mac address assigned to your mac manually (see step 7) or by the DHCP server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point you'll want to start the TFTP server and NFS services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boot into the open firmware (by holding command+option+O+F) and issue the following commands&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
setenv boot-device enet:ip-address-of-linux-server,BootX
setenv boot-args rp=nfs:ip-address-of-linux-server:/tftpboot/:macosx.img
boot
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where ip-address-of-linux-server is... self-explanatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The well familiar Mac boot sequence should start except now you have a little spinning world as logo while it tries to make a connection to the Linux server. You'll probably want to hold command+V while booting the Mac to see what's actually happening and to ensure the whole process is going smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope it helped!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="osx network install"></category><category term="linux network install"></category><category term="leopard network install"></category><category term="fedoraplanet"></category></entry></feed>